<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The devils bow unstringed, or, Some of Thomas Dansons lyes made manifest, : which he hath printed and put to publick view in two pamphlets, the one intituled, The Quakers folly made manifest. And the other, The Quakers wisdom not from above. : And in the first page of his narrative he calleth them undoubted truths, but the wise in heart will not so take them, but will consider better of them, for the wise mans eye is in his head. / By Luke Howard.</title>
            <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2984A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789347</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789347</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2643:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The devils bow unstringed, or, Some of Thomas Dansons lyes made manifest, : which he hath printed and put to publick view in two pamphlets, the one intituled, The Quakers folly made manifest. And the other, The Quakers wisdom not from above. : And in the first page of his narrative he calleth them undoubted truths, but the wise in heart will not so take them, but will consider better of them, for the wise mans eye is in his head. / By Luke Howard.</title>
                  <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694. --  Quakers folly made manifest to all men, or, A true relation of what passed in three disputations at Sandwich, April 12, 13, 19, 1659.</term>
               <term>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694. --  Quakers wisdom not from above.</term>
               <term>Quakers folly made manifest to all men, or, A true relation of what passed in three disputations at Sandwich, April 12, 13, 19, 1659.</term>
               <term>Quakers wisdom not from above.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172656:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Devils Bow UNSTRINGED, OR Some of <hi>Thomas Danſons</hi> Lyes made manifeſt, which he hath Printed and put to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view in two Pamphlets, the one Intituled, <hi>The Quakers Folly made manifeſt.</hi> And the other, <hi>The Quakers Wiſdom not from above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the firſt page of his <hi>Narrative</hi> he calleth them <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubted Truths,</hi> But the wiſe in heart will not ſo take them, but will conſider better of them, for, <hi>The wiſe mans eye is in his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Luke Howard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172656:2"/>
            <p>ANd now <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> if it be not too late, conſider well what thou haſt done, by ſhooting in the Divels Bow, and making uſe of the Divils Weapons, as thou ſayeſt thou haſt done in the 50. page of thy firſt Book, to the oppoſing of the Truth which maketh free all which liveth in it, and ſtirreth up <hi>Cains</hi> nature in all which liveth out of it, and as it is manifeſt it hath done in thee, to the publiſhing of 2 pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets againſt it, filled with the Old mans Dreams made up of lyes; And becauſe thou haſt made uſe of my name in them both ſeveral times, as a ſeale ſet to thy lyes to blinde the ſimple; and for the Truths ſake is it on me as a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to bear my teſtimony againſt thee, and to prove thee ſuch a one as thou haſt both ſaid of, and proved thy ſelf to be, ſhooting in the <hi>Divels Bow,</hi> and making uſe of his Weapons who is the Father of lyes.</p>
            <p>In thy firſt Book, page 49. Thou ſayeſt <hi>that the Quakers came to your Town and made a challenge to the Prieſt to defend their Doctrines and Call;</hi> this I wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt as a lye, or an Arrow ſhot out of the Divels <hi>Bow,</hi> for thou mayeſt remember that we being met together in a place called the <hi>Vickerage-houſe,</hi> thy ſelf and many more came in and paſſed through our Meeting into another Room, and there ſtayed untill thou dideſt hear words ſpoke in our Meeting by one of our friends, <hi>viz. Stephen Huberſtye,</hi> and then you ruſhed all in to us, and after ſome time did gainſay what was ſpoken; but after ſome time of thy gain-ſaying Diſcourſe, for the Truths ſake I asked thee <hi>if thou waſt willing to debate theſe things more at large at another time;</hi> and this is what was propounded by us, which cannot juſtly be called a challenge, and this thou was not at the firſt willing to, but afterwards didſt ſaye, that if I would engage to bring Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> (as thou calleſt him) thou wouldeſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to meet, and thou mayeſt remember this was my anſwer ſeveral times to thee, <hi>That I had not the command of S. F. his Spirit, and ſo could not engage him;</hi> and beſides, for ought I know, he was many ſcores of miles from home, and if thou wouldeſt not appoint to meet with ſome other, that then it might not be: So then thou dideſt agree to meet with ſome other, and the meeting to be that day moneth, witneſſe <hi>Edward Nokes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thou being ſo well skild in ſhooting in the <hi>Divels Bow,</hi> That at that inſtant time dideſt ſhoot out one lye to all the people, <hi>viz.</hi> That I had agreed to bring Mr. <hi>S. F.</hi> the which I denied at that preſent time in the face of all the people, the which they that will be honeſt can witneſſe the truth of, and I am ſure will do; yet ſuch was thy boldneſſe, that thou wouldeſt have one ſhoot more in the Divels Bow, in the old Maſſe-houſe, falſly called St. <hi>Peters Church in Sandwitch,</hi> and there dideſt ſay that the Diſpute was appointed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Mr. <hi>S. F.</hi> and thee, the which I denied again in the face of all the people, and all who are ſingle-hearted on both ſides knows to be true, and thy ſelf alſo, if thou wilt not ſtifle the witneſſe in thy conſcience, yet in thy anger, thou wouldeſt have one great ſhoot more in the Divels Bow, and ſo puts this thy lye in Print amongſt many more to publick view, as a witneſſe againſt thee to the knowledge of many who dares not but ſpeak the truth; and this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony I bear to the Truth againſt thy lyes, that no honeſt mind may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived therewith by thy pretended fair words, whereby thou lieſt in wait to deceive.</p>
            <p>And then in thy ſecond Book thou appeareſt as if thou hadſt fulfilled the worlds Proverb, <hi>viz.</hi> To take Hell and skim the Divel, for Arrows, to wit,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172656:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>lyes to utter, yet ſo great is thy impudency, that thou doſt not bluſh to ſay in the firſt page of thy <hi>Narrative</hi> of the laſt Book, that they are of <hi>undoubted credit,</hi> (mark that) and that to the moſt part of them there is the witneſſes names; but that is juſt the Divels practice to ſlay the Truth with a lye, and give a reaſon for it, and that will appear to be but thy arrogancy and impudency to abuſe the men in citing their names, as witneſſes to thy lyes, contrary to their knowledge, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Davis,</hi> as thou calleſt them, the one Miniſter in <hi>Rumny Marſh,</hi> and the other at <hi>Dover,</hi> as thou haſt writ them; and by them whom we do know let us meaſure all the reſt whom we do not know; moſt of them being ſuch as thou ſeemeſt to be aſhamed of, or at the beſt loath to name them.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning <hi>John Davis,</hi> whom thou ſites to prove that <hi>a Quaker</hi> in <hi>Dover</hi> lying ſick on his death-bed, being asked, by whom he thought to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, ſhould reply, by his own righteouſneſſe, and not by the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt; and I knowing of it to be a lye, as to that friend who died, and for the Truths ſake could not let it paſs without going to <hi>John Davis,</hi> and demanded of him whether ever he informed <hi>Tho. Danſon</hi> of <hi>ſuch a thing,</hi> or ever ſaw that friend in the time of his ſickneſſe, whoſe anſwer was, that he never ſaw him in the time of his ſickneſs, and that he ſcarce knew ſo much as where he dwelt, and this his anſwer was in the preſence of <hi>John Higgins</hi> of <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here <hi>Tho. Danſon,</hi> Behold thy forwardneſſe, and read thy wickedneſs, who haſt made uſe of a mans name contrary to his will, and without his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as himſelf ſaith, to prove thy lyes, and with a whores forehead canſt call them <hi>undoubted truths,</hi> as thou haſt done in thy Pamphlet, therefore lay thy hand upon thy mouth, and let ſhame cover thy face, and never more call thy ſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel, having manifeſted thy ſelf to the contrary, to be a lover and a maker of lyes, and all ſuch are ſtrangers to the Goſpel which is the power of God, but are ſhut out amongſt the dogs.</p>
            <p>And again thou ſayeſt that in <hi>May</hi> laſt there having been ſome diſcourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt one <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Dover</hi> Quaker, and a Miniſter in <hi>Rumney Marſh, viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi> (as thou calleſt him) the next day was appointed for further diſcourſe betwixt them two, but over night the ſaid <hi>Howard</hi> ſent his man and his horſe for Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſometime a Miniſter, and now a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and ſuſpected to be a Jeſuite, and going with him to the place of Meeting, told the people, that ſeeing <hi>S. F.</hi> came accidentally there, he would now leave the diſcourſe to him, and one ſtanding by ſhould ſay that he ſaw <hi>Howards</hi> horſe and man go over night, and that <hi>S. F.</hi> rid into the Town on the ſame horſe the next morning: And this thou ſayeſt is well enough known, that beſides the lyes in their Doctrines, they have not ſo much Moral honeſty as to ſpeak truth in matter of Fact; theſe are thy own words in thy <hi>Narrative,</hi> page the fifth, and to prove it, thou haſt ſet Mr. <hi>Ruſſel</hi> Miniſter in the <hi>Marſh</hi> in the Margent as a witneſſe</p>
            <p>But this I know, that thy proof is ſo ſhort, that its no proof at all; But an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Arrow at large ſhot out of the Divels <hi>Bow,</hi> in which thou art a ſhooting throughout in both thy Pamphlets, but they will return again and ſtick faſt in thy own ſides, and as Darts in thy liver will they be thy burthen; and the Pit thou haſt digged for the innocent, thou muſt fall into thy ſelf; for this is a lye in every part of it, for the diſcourſe was not betwixt me and <hi>William Ruſſell,</hi> neither did I ſend my horſe and man over night for <hi>S. F.</hi> But for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172656:3"/>Truths ſake thus it was; <hi>Edward Burrough</hi> coming to <hi>Dover</hi> to get paſſage for <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and knowing that <hi>S. F.</hi> had ſomething on him to go alſo, asked me, to let my ſon ride down on his horſe (which is a black one, and mine a ray, eaſily to be diſtinguiſhed by all that loves to ſpeak truth) to carry <hi>S. F.</hi> a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and <hi>E. B.</hi> ſent the boy away ſo long before our meeting, that we did think that the boy might be near <hi>S. F.</hi> his houſe. before <hi>William Ruſſel</hi> came into our Meeting, or we knew of any meeting to be; And beſides the Diſpute was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan by a Baptiſt who had been convinced of the Truth, and <hi>Judas</hi> like turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his back upon it, and betrayed it into the hands of the Prieſt, <hi>viz. William Ruſſel,</hi> who was hovering about the window where our Meeting was; and after ſome time he came in and intermedling with the Diſcourſe, the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt left the mannagement of it to him; ſo time being ſhort, <hi>E. B.</hi> and <hi>W. R.</hi> appointed to come again in the morning, which they did, and about the middle of the day; <hi>W. R.</hi> deſired a little time of eaſe, and to meet in the after part of the day in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Church (falſly ſo called) ſo <hi>E. B.</hi> met him there, and then <hi>S. F.</hi> came, and knew nothing of the Diſpute, leſſe, or more, till he came to town, for how could he, the boy being ſent by <hi>E. B.</hi> the morning before the Diſpute began, and neither my ſelf, nor <hi>S. F.</hi> were little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it, but <hi>E. B.</hi> chiefly, by whom that day through the Lords ſtrength Truth was richly made manifeſt, and the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> proved deceivers, and this is a true Relation of this matter, witneſſe <hi>John E'eins, Henry Goodis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo here followeth a true Relation taken from the mouth of <hi>William Ruſſel.</hi> (whom he hath ſet in the Margent to cover his lyes) and to make them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as truth unto the world, by which he manifeſted his inveterate wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and rage againſt the Truth, which appeareth to be very great by his raking together ſuch groundleſſe ſtuffe, and confirming them with ſuch ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling words, ſaying that they are <hi>undoubted Truths,</hi> and that to the moſt of them there is the witneſſes names, but this will be alſo unto thy ſhame) for this is <hi>William Ruſſels</hi> own teſtimony that he hath neither ſpoken, nor writ, nor ſent any manner of way any thing to <hi>Tho. Danſon</hi> about that Diſpute, witneſſe hereunto <hi>John Higgins, John Philley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo he hath made uſe of <hi>William Ruſſels</hi> name, contrary to his will, and without his knowledge to be a falſe witneſſe to his Lies, which is abomination to the Lord. But <hi>Wil. Ruſſel</hi> ſaid that <hi>Nath. Barry</hi> told him that he did inform <hi>Tho. Danſon</hi> of it: Now this <hi>Nath, Barry</hi> is a Prieſt in <hi>Dover,</hi> and Preacheth at the old Maſſe houſe, falſely called St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church; And I aſked him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did Report it to <hi>Tho Danſon,</hi> and he at the firſt was very loth to tell me, as being conſcious of evil in himſelf as I judged; But in his anſwer to me thus he ordered his ſpeech, ſaying <hi>That he heard ſuch a Report, and onely ſpake of it at a Gentlemans houſe where</hi> Tho. Danſon <hi>was, and that he did not think he would have printed it.</hi> And thus they report lyes one to another even as brethren therein, and ſtrengthen themſelves in darkneſs by making lyes their Refuge, and under falſhood hides themſelves, but are afraid to bring or have them brought to the light which is the truth, for that is their condemnation: And thus they fulfill the Scriptures upon themſelves, as the falſe prophets of old did, who watched for evil, and for the halting of the Righteous, and ſaid, Come Report and we will report it: But why do the Heathen rage, and the people imagine a vain thing againſt the Lord and againſt his Annointed, for ſurely in vain is the ſnare laid in the ſight of any bird, for though the prieſts dig as deep as Hell to hide their counſel, and to make a covenant with hell and death, yet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172656:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Truth will diſanull it all, and the overflowing ſcourge will and muſt overtake them in their works of darkneſs, and he that ſitteth in heaven will laugh them to ſcorn, &amp; ſhall have them in deriſion, for now is the Lord a making their folly known unto all men, and they ſhall proceed no further, but ſhall go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and be ſnared and fall and be taken by the traps which they lay, and the pits which they digg for the innocent, in which they ſhall fall in the bowels of their mother the great Whore Myſtery <hi>Babylon,</hi> as a milſtone into the Sea, never to riſe any more, and the day is near at hand wherein it will be ſeen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, even the fullfilling of that which was propheſied of in ages paſt, for the Lord alone will do it for his own name ſake, which the Prieſts have pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and by their lightneſs and by their lying have cauſed the people ſo to do alſo, ſo that from them prophaneſs is gone forth amongſt all people in this preſent age as much as in any, but wo and miſery will be the end of all ſuch, the workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Thomas Danſon,</hi> if we may meaſure all the reſt of thy bitter Arrows ſhot out of the Devils Bow by theſe thy two great witneſſes, we may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them to be ſuch like, and this we have ſufficient ground to do, and that they (to wit) thy Arrowes will never ſlay the Dragon nor bruiſe the head of the old Serpent, which is the Devil, who ruleth in the hearts of all the children of diſobedience, and ſo in thee <hi>Thomas Danſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another thing thou haſt to ſay of me from one of thy brethren, like thy ſelf that met me near <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle, at which time he had much to ſay of friends and truth, but refuſed to tell me his name or the place where he lived, or to meet me in a more publick place to make good his charge; but now thou having raked him up to ſhoot his lye out of thy Bow, he appeareth (or thee for him) who calleſt him the Miniſter of <hi>Word</hi> near <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and ſaying that I ſhould ſay that it was revealed to me by the eternal God that the Prieſts ſhould be deſtroyed, and that by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and this thou bringeſt as all thy proof to evidence three lyes, beſides this, to wit, that a <hi>Quuker</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi> (who as thou ſayeſt had taken upon him to be ſpeaker in that meeting) called our to a Miniſter of the Pariſh as he paſſed by, ſaying, we will have you all down, for now our day is come; which Practiſe we deny.</p>
            <p>And that another in the ſame County ſhould ſay, <hi>that he no more cared to kill a Prieſt then he cared to kill a Dogg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that another ſhould Juſtell a man on the way, having his Wife behind him, and drew out his ſword half way, which was a ſuſpition that he would have killed him [a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou in thy ſuſpicious minde ſaith] had he not been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; but theſe three men thou doſt not name, ſo thy proof in theſe three thou haſt not yet raked up, and except they be ſuch as will ſhoot in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Bow with thee, thou wilt be troubled to make them enter into ſober peoples underſtandings, they are ſo groundleſs, and all this groundleſs ſtuff, the lye which thou haſt laid on me is all the evidence thou haſt produced, as if we were a people in whoſe hearts were blood, of which we are clear, and not like that bloody generation of Prieſts, who lately made an inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>George Booth</hi> and you their brethren, which were loth to read the Proclamation againſt them, here read thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>And if ſuch kind of proof may be taken to brand the innocent, then thy lyes may paſs; but to the contrary, can I bring many witneſſes, and that theſe were my words to the Prieſt I met beſide the Caſtle, or to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to wit, <hi>That the decree of the Lord was gone out and ſealed againſt the Prieſts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172656:4"/>to pluck them up by the roots for their wickedneſs,</hi> witneſs John Hummerdien, of <hi>Dover.</hi> John Marſh, Heſter Warry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that I believe will certainly come to paſs, as truly as ever your Fathers the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and</hi> Love <hi>your brothers, who loſt their Heads on</hi> Tower hill <hi>for their wickedneſs, which may be looked upon as true figures of the downfal of your whole body of oppoſers of the truth, for now is the Lord a ſearching out your hidden things of</hi> Eſau, <hi>and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them to publick view:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Witneſs the late Proclamation, by which many of you were proclaimed Rebells and Traytors to the peace of your Countrey. The day is come, and a coming which ſhall declare every mans works, and that all ſhall be tryed by fire, and there is nothing which will ſtand in Covenant with the Lord, but what will indure the fire, therefore let none be deceived, profeſſors or not profeſſors, covered or not covered with names of Saints or Churches, God will not be mocked, but ſuch as every man ſows, ſuch ſhall he reap; if they ſow to the fleſh, they muſt of the fleſh reap corruption, but if they ſow to the ſpirit, <hi>viz.</hi> That which reproveth them for ſin, they ſhall of the Spirit reap life everlaſting, for its reproofs of inſtruction are the way to life, and alſo he that liveth after the fleſh ſhall dye, but he that through the ſpirit (which reproveth the World of ſin, righteouſneſs &amp; of Judgment) mortifieth the deeds of the fleſh, he ſhall live; for in every nation, and amongſt all people, he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted of him, and the fear of the Lord is to depart from iniquity, and a fountain of life to depart from the wayes of death, and the fear of the Lord keepeth the heart clean, ſo all people feel that which keepeth the heart clean, for it is the pure in heart onely ſhall ſee God, and there is none that can ſee his face with peace, and live in the firſt nature, but as a conſuming fire will his appearance be to all ſuch who have a life in the tranſgreſſion, or treſpaſſing againſt that which ſhews them ſin and iniquity.</p>
            <p>And now to thy two Queſtions which thou makeſt in thy Title page, <hi>viz. If it be not ſo now, who will make thee a lyer, and make thy ſpeech nothing worth, and what thou haſt done, is there not a cauſe, ſayeſt thou.</hi> (No cauſe to lye, ſay I) And all this thou haſt done to confirm people in a bad opinion of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and thou truſteſt that it will do it, as thou ſayeſt in thy confuſed preface, in the beginning of which thou ſayeſt, <hi>thou art come once more upon the Stage</hi> (and its true, more like a ſtage Player then a Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) <hi>not without a bluſh;</hi> and truly according to the Worlds proverb, thou mayeſt indeed bluſh for ſhame to utter ſo many lyes in the face of the Son, which is right ſtage player like, whoſe life and trade is to lye, and this thou haſt done, by which the hands of the wicked are ſtrengthned, that he ſhould not return from his wickedneſs, but rejoyce in his iniquity, and Joyneth himſelf with thee againſt the truth, and ſo thou mayeſt have thy prayer an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, which thou makeſt in the end of this preface, <hi>viz. That the Reader may hold faſt that Doctrine which he hath already learned;</hi> and if thou meaneſt ſuch Doctrines as are to be learned of thee (as no doubt thou doeſt) which is to plead for ſin as long as he liveth in the body, Then where and when muſt he glorifie God, with his ſpirit and with his body, ſeeing in the Grave there is no remembrance of him, and he whoſe converſation is not ordered aright whileſt he is in the body doth not glorifie him, and alſo none glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God but ſuch as bringeth forth fruit to his Spirit, which reproveth man for all ſin, and leadeth all out of ſin which hearkens to and obeys its reproofs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172656:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and as many as are led by the ſpirit of God, they are the Sons of God, and none elſe, and they glorifie their Father which is in Heaven, by there converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which is alſo in Heaven, which is without covetouſneſs, pride, or any thing which worketh an abomination or maketh a lye, all which fruits is ſhut out of the Kingdom; here read thy own ſtate and be not deceived with vain hopes, but read within thee, that the hope of the hypocrite ſhall periſh, and that without remedy; and ſo in truth and in the fear of the Lord, I have proved thee a lyer, and ſo thy ſpeech to be nothing worth, and this ſhall ſtand over thy head a full anſwer to thy queſtions, and to this let the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in all Conſciences anſwer that this readeth, and I know it will do in all where it is ſuffered to ſpeak, that knoweth any thing as eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the matter which occaſions theſe Lines to be written to thee <hi>T. D.</hi> by which thou art put by thy truſt, which thou in thy Preface ſpeakeſt of and truſteſt to, to beget in people a bad opinion of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> except it be in ſuch as thy ſelf is, who makeſt lyes thy refuge, and under falſehood hideth thy ſelf: But this know, that thou and all ſuch, that to ſpeak the truth is alwayes beſt, every man to his neighbour, the which if thou hadſt learned it within thee, as plain and as well as thou canſt read it without thee, then thou wouldſt have known a bridle to thy Tongue before this time, and never have been raking abroad for lyes, but for want of that thy Religion is vaine, as ſaith the Scriptures of truth, which we believe, and ſhews the life of as a witneſs againſt thee and all the vain talkers and diſputers of this World, about the huſks, which is the letter, on which the Swines do feed, who rent and tear the Lambs and lives in the liberty of the fleſh, out of the life of them wherein the Worlds friendſhip ſtandeth, which is enmity againſt God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king honour one of another, and not the honour which is of God alone, which is to live in his fear, and how can ſuch believe or know the faith which giveth victory over the world, and in this ſtate thou haſt manifeſted thy ſelf to be in a large meaſure, by thy lying and flattery with thoſe worthy perſons which thou in thy Pamphlets ſpeaks of, and this will appear to all that have but moral honeſty in them, and ſo much ſobriety as to ponder thy lines and the weight of thy words, and the grounds thou ſpeakeſt them from, the which to him who liveth and walketh in the light of the Lord, will appear to be from the bottomleſs pit, wherein they muſt go again with the lyar, the beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, which is the proper and the appointed place for them all.</p>
            <p>And this I have writ for the clearing of my own Conſcience and the truth, which is my life, ſo far as in brief it might be done, and I concerned ſo to do, &amp; have laid the lys on the lyars head, &amp; turned the Devils fiery darts back into his own Quiver again, and in this I have cleared my Conſcience, which is a true and faithfull teſtimony born by me, who am a knower and a lover of the <hi>Quakers</hi> principles, becauſe I know and feel that they lead out of ſin, and alſo out of the nature which pleadeth for ſin; for he that believeth hath the witneſſe in himſelf, in which I reſt in peace, and remain a true friend and a lover of the Seed of God in all men, but an enemy to the ſeed of the Serpent, in all without reſpect to the perſons of any; and this teſtimony is true, born by me <hi>Luke Howard</hi> againſt <hi>Thomas Danſons</hi> lyes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dover</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 15th. <hi>of the</hi> 10th. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:172656:5"/>

               <signed>L. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>THis my teſtimony to the truth is true, and alſo thine <hi>T. D.</hi> is falſe, which thou haſt Printed againſt the truth, my ſelf, and others, and if thou wouldeſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o honeſt as to ſpeak the truth, thou knoweſt it is ſo; but if in thy hardneſs of heart and boldneſs of face, ſhouldeſt yet ſay to the contrary, let not thy ſpeech of it at a rich mans Table (which you Prieſts love to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to ſerve your God, to wit, your bellies) ſerve the turn, but let the truth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the face of the Son, and if thou dareſt affirm that thou haſt Printed nought but truth, then make thy ſelf ſtrong, and gather together thy witneſſes, to wit, the four Prieſts mentioned in thy pamphlet to prove thy lyes, and meet me publickly in <hi>Dover</hi> or <hi>Sandwich</hi> Market place, and let timely notice be given, that much people may hear of it and meet with us, and I may be ready to meet thee in the fear of the Lord, with witneſſes alſo to prove the truth outwardly beſides the Teſtimony of my own Conſcience within, which is more to me then a thouſand witneſſes without, and let the lyar bear his own burden, and if this be refuſed by thee, I ſay again, ceaſe uſing of thy Tongue at <hi>Rich mens Tables,</hi> for that will be thy ſhame to boaſt in lyes, for the day is ſo far come on that many of them ſee through the deceit of the Prieſts, though they have not ſo much yet born up in them as to deny you, but your folly doth appear to many of them and it will to all men, to the fulfilling of the Scriptures; ſo that I ſay again and again, that the decree of the Lord is to pluck you up by the roots for your wickedneſs, your pride, lightneſs, lying and covetouſneſs, and for theſe things will ye ſtink as a dung-hill againſt the Sun, and that all the ſtrength of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhall not help you, for the Scripture will be fulfilled upon you, <hi>viz.</hi> Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm, when all whoſe confidence is in the Lord, and not in Princes, ſhall be as Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> which ſhall never be moved, and herein lyeth our ſtrength, and in him is our joy full, and if it had not been ſo we had long ſince been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmed, to the rejoycing of you Prieſts who have long looked for it, who in your hearts ſay againſt the appearance of the heir of all things in this age, as your murthering Brethren of old did againſt the appearance of him in ages paſt, <hi>viz.</hi> This is the heir, come let us kill him that the inheriance may be ours But the work is in the hand of the Lord now, as ever it was, and by him carried on, who is bringing great things to paſs out of your reach and ſight, but this is your inheritance and due reward from the Lord to be filled with the fruit of your own doings, and that will be a burden heavy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and too heavy for you to bear, I am ſure of it, who am one that underſtandeth well, and feeleth what I ſay, and therefore cannot but pity you, yea I can truly ſay pity you all, though <hi>abuſed by you and hated of you and your Generation,</hi> yet dare not render to you evil for evil, but contrary wiſe good to you and all men, by which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be made manifeſt to you and to the witneſſe of God in you, otherwiſe by name,</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
